<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-28T17:20:35+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Centuria Games</title><subtitle>Official Website of the Hound of Ulster</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Making of Our Main Character: Cu Chulainn!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/2025/10/19/making-of-cu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making of Our Main Character: Cu Chulainn!" /><published>2025-10-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-10-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/2025/10/19/making-of-cu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/2025/10/19/making-of-cu/"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post outlines the creation workflow developed within the program for our
final game project. Prepared by Lead Artist Elizabeth Guerrero Mendoza, UPC student
specializing in technical art.</p>

<video autoplay="" muted="" loop="" id="myVideo">
  <source src="/CenturiaGames/assets/videos/cu_spin.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<h3 id="concept--planning">Concept &amp; Planning</h3>
<p>The first part before everything was to get the overall feeling of the character and
after some research and brainstorming, there were some proposals based on the 
character’s first concept.</p>

<p>The idea was to adapt it more into a 3d model, whether that be accentuate 
proportions, check if there’s too much noise in certain areas and iterate how the 
whole silhouette reads, plus adding more storytelling in the general looks.</p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image1.png" /></p>

<h3 id="high-poly-sculpting">High Poly Sculpting</h3>
<p>Here it was to find the flow in some areas of the concept such as the fur and hair, 
or the shoulderpad, that took many trials and errors, a modified plane, a base in 
Maya, a sphere, the sun rays different meshes, a personal preference is to jump 
between topogun and zbrush to keep a shape I like and polish to make sense in 
geometry, same with the body, and plenty of pieces, basically all of them save for 
the hair and fur, once I had that, then did I went all in on the HP details.</p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image2.png" /></p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image3.png" /></p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image4.png" /></p>

<h3 id="retopology--uv-unwrapping">Retopology &amp; UV Unwrapping</h3>
<p>With my workflow of jumping between programs I did most of the retopo side by side 
with the HP, the only thing that really took a while was the hair/fur so when the 
UVs had to be done, they could be understood nicely what was each part.</p>

<p>Also perfect time to do a quick test in Mixamo, just to make sure the model deforms 
okay before texturing.</p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image5.png" /></p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image6.png" /></p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image7.png" /></p>

<h3 id="baking">Baking</h3>
<p>For a better bake everything was arranged in explode.</p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image8.png" /></p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/image9.png" /></p>

<h3 id="texturing">Texturing</h3>
<p>What zbrush to topogun, substance to photoshop, jumping from one to another. 
Creating a grayscale material that then I can send to photoshop to add colors 
where it’s way faster to iterate. Once pleased with the result, send it back to 
Substance Painter for polishing small details and review the PBRs (Physically-Based 
Rendering) making sure the metal looks metallic, leather rough, etc. Also where I 
made final tweaks, like giving him a meaner frown or simplifying the colors after 
getting feedback.</p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/imageA.png" /></p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/imageB.png" /></p>

<h3 id="rigging-posing-and-presentation">Rigging, Posing and Presentation</h3>
<p>I made a basic rig, which later turned into the first iteration of many, but that’s 
another story, very specific to what I wanted to showcase here such as, eyebrows ears
and the 2 bangs to each side, the weight paint was still a test at this time.</p>

<p>And Voila! We have our main character ready for the first tests of animation!</p>

<p><img src="/CenturiaGames/assets/images/article1/imageC.png" /></p>

<p>Elizabeth Guerrero Mendoza, Lead Artist at Centuria Games</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Celtic" /><category term="Development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post outlines the creation workflow developed within the program for our final game project. Prepared by Lead Artist Elizabeth Guerrero Mendoza, UPC student specializing in technical art.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First blog post</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/2025/04/15/welcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First blog post" /><published>2025-04-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/2025/04/15/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CenturiaGames/2025/04/15/welcome/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello World! This is the first post of our devlog.</p>

<p>We will be sharing sneak peaks of how the development is going, videos, concept art and more!.  🌿⚔️</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Celtic" /><category term="development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World! This is the first post of our devlog.]]></summary></entry></feed>